A Guide to the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1838-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series 1: Literary Manuscripts
  - "Leaves of Grass," 1857-1871, 230 leaves, handwritten (Bowers #31). (Folders 50-51)
    - [Hours continuing long, sore], pages 71-72: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, handwritten, leaf 1 (9.5 x 9 cm.); leaf 2 (14.5 x 9 cm. pasted to 5 x 9.5 cm.).
      On two pieces of white wove paper, the first cut down to 9.5 x 9 cm. and the second comprising two sections (14.5 x 9 and 5 x 9.5 cm.) joined by means of a strip of pink paper. In brown-black ink, with revisions in the same ink and in pencil. Pinholes mostly at top and in center of leaves. Whitman penciled in the numbers 11 and 12 (apparently over other numbers) in the lower-left corner of each page; his partly erased pencil note "(finished in/ the other city)" appears on the first page. The ornamental number "VIII" replaces a deleted ornamental "IX" on the first page, and the top of another "IX" appears at the foot of the second page, beneath a wavy line indicating the end of the poem. Whitman removed the lower section of page 2 from the top of current leaf Vol. 1, p. 132 ("I dreamed in a dream of a/ city..."). This poem, the eighth in the sequence Live Oak, with Moss, became section 9 of Calamus in 1860. This was its only appearance in Leaves. The first page contains what would become verses 1-3 in 1860, and the second ("Hours discouraged, distracted,") contains lines 4-12.
      - Page 71, Volume 1. Hours continuing long, sore
      - Page 72, Volume 1. Hours discouraged, distracted
      - Page 73, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: Calamus #9
    - You bards of ages hence, Pages 74-75, Volume 1: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, leaf 1 (8 x 9 cm.); leaf 2 (14.5 x 9.5 cm. pasted to 5.5 x 9.5 cm.).
      On two sections of white wove paper, the first cut down to 8 x 9 cm. and the second a composite of two pieces pasted together, the top measuring 14.5 x 9.5 and the bottom 5.5 x 9.5 cm. In black ink, with a few revisions in the same ink. Pinholes at top and in center of both pages. Whitman numbered the first 9 1/2 and the second 10, in pencil, in the lower-left corner of each leaf. The Roman numeral is inscribed in an ornamental style, and the poem terminates with a wavy line. The seventh poem in the sequence Live Oak, with Moss, became section 10 of Calamus in 1860 and was permanently retitled Recorders Ages Hence in 1867. The lines on the first page correspond to verses 1-3 of the 1860 version, and those on the second page ("Publish my name and hang up/ my picture...") to lines 4-11.
      - Page 74, Volume 1. You bards of ages hence!
      - Page 75, Volume 1. Publish my name and hang up
      - Page 76, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: Calamus #10
      - Page 77, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: Calamus #10, continued.
    - When I heard at the close of, pages 78-79, Volume 1: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, 15 x 9.5 cm.
      On two leaves of white wove paper, both measuring 15 x 9.5 cm.; the lower half of the second page is pasted over with a section of white paper (8 x 9 cm.) containing four revised verses. In black ink, with revisions in the same ink and in pencil. Pinholes mostly at top of both pages. Whitman numbered the pages 4 and 5, in pencil, in their lower-left corners. The third section of Live Oak, with Moss (with ornamental Roman numeral), this poem became section 11 of Calamus in 1860 and was permanently retitled When I Heard at the Close of the Day in 1867. For an earlier draft of the poem numbered V please see the verso of leaves 15-16 of Premonition (Vol 1, pp. 15-16). Bowers (p. 88) supplies the three earlier lines concealed by the paste-on revision to the second leaf. The lines on the first page correspond to verses 1-5 of the 1860 version, and those on the second page ("And when I thought how/ my friend,...") to lines 6-13.
      - Page 78, Volume 1. When I heard at the close of
      - Page 79, Volume 1. And when I thought how
      - Page 80, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #11
    - "To a new personal admirer," pages 81-82, Volume 1: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, leaf 1 (13 x 11.5 cm.); leaf 2 (20 x 16 cm.).
      On two pieces of white wove paper, 13 x 11.5 and 20 x 16 cm., in brown-black ink, with substantial revisions in the same ink. Pinholes mostly at center and in left margins of both pages. This poem, featuring a new first line, became section 12 of Calamus in 1860; in 1867 Whitman dropped the last 2 1/2 lines and permanently retitled it Are you the New Person Drawn Toward Me? The first page contains verses corresponding to lines 2-3 of the 1860 version, and the lines on the second page ("Do you suppose you can easily/ be my lover,...") became verses 4-11.
      - Page 81, Volume 1. "To a new personal admirer"
      - Page 82, Volume 1. Do you suppose you can easily
      - Page 83, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #12
      - Page 84, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #12 continued.
    - "Buds," page 85, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21.5 x 13 cm.
      On pink leaf (21.5 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with minor revisions in the same ink.A few pinholes at top and near center. A pencil question mark appears in parentheses in the upper-right corner. The number 52 appears to have been revised from 51. After adding several verses, Whitman designated this poem section 13 of Calamus in the 1860 Leaves, and, after dropping the first two and last three lines of the 1860 version, permanently retitled it Roots and Leaves Themselves Alone in 1867.
    - Page 86, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #13
    - "Calamus-Leaves," page 87, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 15 x 9 cm.
      On white wove leaf, 15 x 9 cm., in black ink, with the title Live Oak, with Moss stricken out and Calamus-Leaves added in light brown ink, and with one small revision in blue pencil. Whitman numbered this page 1 in pencil. The first section of the original sequence Live Oak, with Moss, this became section 14 of Calamus in 1860 and was permanently retitled Not Heat Flames up and Consumes in the 1867 Leaves.
    - Page 88, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #14
    - "Confession-Drops," page 89, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21.5 x 12 cm.
      On verso of light blue Williamsburgh tax blank (21.5 x 12 cm.), in light ink, with no revisions. Pinholes at top and in center. This poem became section 15 of Calamus in 1860, and, with the addition of a new first line, was retitled Trickle, Drops in 1867.
    - Page 90, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #15
    - "Leaf," pages 91-92, Volume 1: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, handwritten, 21.5 x 13 cm.
      On two pink leaves (both 21.5 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with extensive revisions in the same ink, in pencil, and in fine pen. Pinholes mostly in center of both leaves, but also at top and in left margins. The original title was Leaflet. On the second page Whitman added, in a combination of normal and blue pencil, the number 43 (1/2). With the addition of a new first line ("1. Who is now reading this?") the poem became section 16 of Calamus in 1860; the lines on the first draft page correspond to verses 2-8 and those on the second page ("Or as if interior in me") to verses 9-10. This was the first and last appearance of the poem during Whitman's lifetime: he rejected it from his Blue Book Copy of Leaves in 1860.
      - Page 91, Volume 1. "Leaf"
      - Page 92, Volume 1. Or as if interior in me
      - Page 93, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #16
      - Page 94, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #16, continued.
    - "Poemet," pages 95-96, Volume 1: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm.
      On two pink leaves (21 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in the same ink and in light ink. Pinholes in center, at top, and in top-left corner. This poem was originally titled Leaf and apparently numbered 78; Whitman inscribed its new title, Poemet, in light ink. It became section 17 of Calamus in 1860, with the lines on the first leaf corresponding to verses 1-7 and those on the second ("And what I dreamed I will/ henceforth tell...") to verses 8-13 of the first published version. Retitled Of Him I Love Day and Night in 1867, it was transferred to the Whispers of Heavenly Death cluster in Passage to India in 1871. In 1881 Whitman incorporated it, with the rest of the cluster, in the main body of Leaves.
      - Page 95, Volume 1. "Poemet"
      - Page 96, Volume 1. And what I dreamed I will
      - Page 97, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #17
      - Page 98, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #17, continued.
    - City of my walks and joys!, page 99, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 8.5 x 10 cm. pasted to 20 x 16 cm.
      On a composite leaf consisting of two pieces of white wove paper, 8.5 x 10 and 20 x 16 cm.; the smaller section (in light brown ink, with few revisions) is pasted over some lines in the top-left corner of the larger piece (in dark brown ink), from the top of which other lines were cut off. Whitman made extensive revisions to the larger piece in the same dark brown ink and in pencil before adding the smaller section. On the verso of the larger piece appears an extensively revised pencil draft of the first poem in Enfans d'Adam (see Vol. 1, p. 35; the lines on the composite page's verso represent an earlier draft of the poem). The verses on the current recto of the composite leaf became section 18 of Calamus in 1860; the poem was permanently retitled City of Orgies in 1867.
    - Page 100, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #18
    - I saw in Louisiana a, Pages 101-102, Volume 1: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, handwritten, 15 x 9.5 cm.
      On two leaves of white wove paper, both 15 x 9.5 cm., in black ink, with extensive revisions in the same ink, in light brown ink, and in pencil. Pinholes mostly at top and in center of both pages. Whitman numbered the pages 2 and 3 in pencil. This was originally the second section of the sequence Live Oak, with Moss (one of the deleted lines reads "I write/ these pieces, and name/ them after it [the Louisiana live-oak];"), with ornamental Roman numeral. It became section 20 of Calamus in 1860; the lines on the first manuscript page correspond to verses 1-7, and those on the second ("It is not needed to remind/ me...") to verses 8-13. The poem was retitled I saw in Louisiana a Live-Oak Growing in 1867.
      - Page 101, Volume 1. I saw in Louisiana a live oak growing
      - Page 102, Volume 1. It is not needed to remind
      - Page 103, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #20
      - Page.104, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #20, continued.
    - "As of Eternity," pages 105-106, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 2 leaves, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm.
      On two leaves of pink paper, both 21 x 13 cm., in black ink, with minor revisions in the same ink. Pinholes mostly in center and at top of both pages. This poem became section 21 of Calamus in 1860; the lines on the first manuscript page became verses 1-6, and those on the second ("I hear not the volumes of/ sound merely—...") became 7-9. Retitled That Music Always Round Me in 1867, it was transferred in 1871 to the Whispers of Heavenly Death cluster in Passage to India. In 1881 Whitman incorporated it, with the rest of the cluster, in the main body of Leaves.
      - Page 105, Volume 1. "As of Eternity"
      - Page 106, Volume 1. I hear not the volumes of
      - Page 107, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #21
      - Page 108, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #21, continued.
    - "To A Stranger," pages 109-110, Volume 1: 1857-1859, 2 leaves, 21 x 13 cm.
      On two leaves of pink paper, both 21 x 13 cm., in black ink, with revisions in the same ink and in light ink. Pinholes mostly in center and in left margin of each page. This poem was first numbered 94, and the first word was "Stranger"; Whitman penciled in a question mark, in parentheses, next to the title. It was numbered section 22 of Calamus in 1860: the lines on the first page correspond to verses 1-6 of the 1860 version, and those on the second ("You give me the pleasure") to verses 7-10. Whitman reintroduced the title To a Stranger in the 1867 Leaves.
      - Page 109, Volume 1. "To A Stranger"
      - Page 110, Volume 1. You give me the pleasure
      - Page 111, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #22
      - Page 112, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #22, continued.
    - This moment as I sit alone, page 113, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 14.5 x 9.5 cm.
      On one leaf of white wove paper, in dark brown ink, with revisions in pencil. Pinholes in center and at top. Whitman penciled in the number 6 in the lower-left corner. The fourth poem in the original sequence Live Oak, with Moss (with ornamental Roman numeral), it became section 23 of Calamus in 1860 and was permanently retitled This Moment, Yearning and Thoughtful in 1867.
    - Page 114, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #23
    - "Prairie-Grass," page 115, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21 x 13 cm.
      On one leaf of pink paper (21 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in an even blacker ink and in pencil. Pinholes in center. The poem was originally numbered 53. In 1860 Whitman designated it section 25 of Calamus, transforming the title into a new first line and expanding the original first line into verses 2-4. In 1867 he further revised it, permanently retitling it The Prairie-Grass Dividing.
    - Page 116, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #25
    - "Razzia," page 117, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21 x 12.5 cm.
      On one leaf of pink paper (21 x 12.5 cm.), in black ink, with minor revisions in the same ink. Pinholes in center. This poem was originally numbered 83. With the addition of the new first lines "We two boys together clinging,/ One the other never leaving..." and attendant revisions it became section 26 of Calamus in 1860, and was permanently retitled We Two Boys Together Clinging in 1867.
    - Page 118, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #26
    - "Leaf (O dying! Always dying!)," page 119, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21.5 x 12 cm.
      On one light blue Williamsburgh tax blank (21.5 x 12 cm.), in dark brown ink, with revisions in fine pen and pencil. Whitman penciled in a question mark, in parentheses, next to the title. With the addition of the new first line "O love!" this became section 27 of Calamus in 1860. In the 1867 Leaves it was retitled O Living Always—Always Dying! Whitman next transferred it to the Passage to India supplement bound in with Leaves, where it reappeared in 1876; in the 1881 Leaves Whitman permanently added it to the cluster Whispers of Heavenly Death.
    - Page 120, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #27
    - "Leaf (A promise to Indiana)," page 121, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 22 x 13 cm.
      On one leaf of pink paper (22 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in the same ink. Pinholes mostly in center. The original title was Leaflet, and the original number seems to have been 70. After substantial revision (including the addition of the new first line "A promise and gift to California,") this poem became section 30 of Calamus in 1860. Whitman further revised the poem before including it, permanently retitled A Promise to California, in the 1867 Leaves.
    - Page 122, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #30
    - "Leaf (What place is besieged)," Page 123, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21.5 x 13 cm.
      On one leaf of pink paper (21.5 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with a fair copy of the poem at the bottom of the leaf and a deleted draft featuring heavy revisions in the same ink and in pencil at the top. This poem was originally numbered 68, and its title was Leaflet—. In 1860 it became the second numbered verse paragraph of section 31 of Calamus. In 1867 Whitman split up the two paragraphs and made them separate poems; these verses were moved to a position between the Calamus and a Leaves of Grass cluster and permanently retitled What Place Is Besieged? In 1881 the poem was transferred to the cluster Inscriptions.
    - Page 124, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #31
    - Here the frailest leaves of me, page 125, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 15 x 9.5 cm.
      On one leaf of white wove paper (15 x 9.5 cm.), in medium-brown ink, with one revision in the same ink. Pinholes mostly at top and in center. The two sets of verses are divided by a short horizontal line. In 1860 the first set, with the addition of a new first line ("Here my last words, and the most baffling,") became section 44 of Calamus; the poem was permanently retitled Here the Frailest Leaves of Me, and the new first line dropped, in 1867. The second set was revised to form section 38 of Calamus in 1860; in 1867 it was further revised and retitled Fast Anchor'd, Eternal, O Love.
    - Page 126, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #44
    - Page 127, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #38
    - A leaf for hand-in-hand, page 128, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 14.5 x 9 cm.
      On one leaf of white wove paper (14.5 x 9 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in pencil. Pinholes in center and at top. A blue-pencil number 3 appears in the upper right corner over an erased 9. With substantial additions and revisions this evolved into section 37 of Calamus in 1860; after further revision it became A Leaf for Hand in Hand in 1867.
    - Page 129, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #37
    - Earth!, page 130, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 14.5 x 9.5 cm.
      On one leaf of white wove paper (14.5 x 9.5 cm.), in brown-black ink, with revisions in lighter ink (including the deletion, undone in 1860, of the phrase "My likeness!" after "Earth!"). Pinholes mostly at top and in center. Whitman penciled in the number 15 in the lower-left corner. Originally poem XI in the sequence Live Oak, with Moss (with the Roman numeral ornamentally drawn), this was revised to become section 36 of Calamus in 1860. In 1867 Whitman retitled the poem Earth! My Likeness!
    - Page 131, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #36
    - I dreamed in a dream of a, page 132, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 9.5 x 9 cm.
      On one leaf of white wove paper cut down to 9.5 x 9 cm., in brown-black ink, with revisions in pencil. Pinholes at top and in center. Whitman numbered the leaf 13, in pencil, in the lower-left corner. The excised top portion of the leaf became the bottom section of page 2 (Vol. 1, p. 72), the poem (eighth in the sequence Live Oak, with Moss ) beginning "Hours continuing long, sore/ and heavy-hearted..." In 1860 this poem was substantially revised to form section 34 of Calamus; in 1867 it was retitled I Dreamed in a Dream.
    - Page 133, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #34
    - What think you I have, page 134, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 8.5 x 9 cm. pasted to 6.5 x 9 cm.
      On a composite leaf of white wove paper consisting of two sections (8.5 x 9 and 6.5 x 9 cm.) pasted together. Both sections are in black ink but, as Bowers notes, the lower verses were inscribed using a darker, thicker pen; the upper section is unrevised, but the lower section bears several alterations in the original ink. Pinholes at top of both sections and in the current center. Whitman numbered the page 9, in pencil, in the lower-left corner. Originally the sixth section of the sequence Live Oak, with Moss, this poem was revised to form section 32 of Calamus in 1860, and in 1867 was retitled What Think You I Take My Pen in Hand?
    - Page 135, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #32
    - Sometimes, page 136, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 15 x 9.5 cm.
      On one leaf of white wove paper (15 x 9.5 cm.), in light brown ink, with one revision in the same ink. Pinholes at top and in center. A blue pencil mark, possibly the number 4, has been inscribed in the upper right corner. Bowers notes that the page bears the imprint of a papermaker's lozenge die, perhaps that of Platner and Smith of Lee, Massachusetts. This poem became section 39 of Calamus in 1860; in 1867 Whitman replaced the third line with a new one and permanently retitled the poem Sometimes with One I Love.
    - Page 137, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #39
    - Page 138, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: Calamus "#39," continued.
    - To the young man, page 139, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 15 x 9 cm.
      On one leaf of white wove paper (15 x 9 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in the same ink and in pencil. Whitman also penciled in the page number 16 in the lower-left corner. Pinholes in center and at top. This page bears the same papermaker's mark as Vol. 1, p. 136. Twelfth in the original sequence Live Oak, with Moss (with ornamental Roman numeral), it became section 42 of Calamus in 1860. In 1867 Whitman changed the poem to an apostrophe, adding the first line "O Boy of the West!" (later removed) and permanently retitling it To a Western Boy.
    - Page 140, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #42
    - "To One Who Will Understand," page 141, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 21.5 x 13 cm.
      On one leaf of pink paper (21.5 x 13 cm.), in black ink, with revisions in the same ink, in pencil, and in fine ink (in that order). Pinholes mostly in center. Originally titled To Those Who Will Understand and numbered 100 (then 101, then the current ?100 in the fine pen). This was revised to form section 41 of Calamus in 1860 and was permanently retitled Among the Multitude in the 1867 Leaves.
    - Page 142, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #41
    - O you whom I often and silently come where you are, page 143, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 14.5 x 9 cm.
      On one leaf of white wove paper (14.5 x 9 cm.), in brown-black ink, with revisions in the same ink. Pinholes mostly at the top, with a few lower down. The tenth section of the original sequence Live Oak, with Moss (with ornamental Roman numeral), this was reformatted and renumbered but otherwise left unrevised as section 43 of Calamus in 1860. In 1867 Whitman permanently retitled it O You Whom I Often and Silently Come.
    - Page 144, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #43
    - That shadow, page 145, Volume 1. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 17 x 9.5 cm.
      One one leaf of lined light blue wove paper (17 x 9.5 cm.), in pencil, with one pencil revision. Only two sets of pinholes, both in center. This was revised to become section 40 of Calamus in 1860; in 1867 it was retitled That Shadow, My Likeness.
    - Page 146, Volume 1. 1860 edition as published: "Calamus" #40
    - "To one a century hence, or any number of centuries hence," 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 10 x 13 cm. pasted to 11.5 x 13 cm.